Michael Burr: Hi, everybody. A lot of people are away at the Macaulay 2 conference this week, so it's a small meeting, but
Michael Burr: the first thing that's gonna happen is Andrew's gonna go over his pull request, and we're gonna get feedback from Mike on
Michael Burr: Whether things are making sense or not.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yes, this is the draft pull request into Michael's A-rings, and if you look up files changed…
Andrew Tawfeek: It's just headers to all the .hp files, and it's been prefaced by AI. This has gone, these were all generated by Codex, GPT 5.5, and,
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, from… the first time that this was posted, Michael had left a comment mentioning…
Andrew Tawfeek: that they were struggling to capture the big picture, and there wasn't a good uniformity across all the headers. So I fed those back into Codex, and it did try to make it a bit more uniform.
Andrew Tawfeek: But it's struggling with front-end, like, human… it… I mean, because it really just generates us using what it could find in the codebase,
Andrew Tawfeek: It, Michael noted during the last meeting that it isn't quite aligning with the human use cases of how we actually use Macaulay day-to-day.
Michael Burr: I'll be specific about what my concern was. Looking at the second paragraph, I'm not sure that…
Michael Burr: They're all the… they're all the same.
Michael Stillman: Oh, okay.
Michael Burr: Essentially, about how this interacts with concrete ring. It may be… Backwards from how…
Michael Burr: I'm… one might want to think about it.
Michael Burr: Because my… my understanding was that concrete ring is coming from the front end, and this is…
Michael Burr: Sort of peeling off and just working with the underlying structure.
Michael Burr: But maybe you should have a quick read of… of one of these, because they're all very similar, and just sort of see…
Michael Stillman: I mean, a concrete ring… so a ring is this, is just this…
Michael Stillman: abstract class, and a concrete ring are various implementations of that, right? And then there are other, concrete rings… things that would be concrete rings, rings that are, are, you know, that are subclass ring and you can use. And so concrete ring is one of those for each A-ring. That's all.
Michael Burr: Andrew, could you go up a little bit to… Yeah, like,
Michael Burr: like, this one is sort of a good… this one's a perfectly fine example. They're all very similar. If you want to take a look at the…
Michael Burr: At the new stuff and see if you agree with the interpretation or not.
Michael Stillman: This header declares the airing implementation.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, so the line that says, the class follows the simple A-ring contract for lifetime and arithmetic… arithmetic. First of all, it doesn't make sense.
Andrew Tawfeek: Oh, I was trying to find the exact, okay, here, I'll go back to the same file.
Michael Burr: I think it's hoping for arithmetic.
Andrew Tawfeek: Not here.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay, there we go. I'll just stay right here.
Michael Stillman: Contract for lifetime and arithmetic over that story.
Andrew Tawfeek: Right, okay.
Michael Stillman: Okay, so it does make sense, but,
Michael Stillman: But over that storage? What does that even mean? You know, it's just a little, it's a…
Michael Stillman: So, I mean, the idea is that the simple A-ring is just an example of a, of an A-ring that can be plugged into lots of different situations, right? So, if we were actually using Rust.
Michael Stillman: Or if we were using C++23, or whatever, 20, we could do this as, contracts of some sort, right? Or concepts. Concepts in C++… what is it called in Rust? Probably just an interface or something like that, I don't know.
Michael Stillman: I forget what the name of it is.
Michael Stillman: But it's not so… and it does…
Michael Stillman: So, it is a contract for a lifetime, but what is the contract? The contract is that
Michael Stillman: you are responsible for, for management of memory. When you do an init of something, it's like the GMP… really, it's matching the GMP interface
Michael Stillman: Which sucks the big wazoo, but it's kind of consistent, and…
Michael Stillman: And you have a lot more control over memory allocation stuff because of the way they do it. So… so, for better or worse, that… so I would say it's… it's really for, you know, it mimics the…
Michael Stillman: The…
Michael Stillman: I don't know how to say it, I have to think about it. Anyway, let's, go to the next paragraph here.
Michael Burr: I mean, the point of this is to get feedback so that
Michael Burr: these can be improved. So, anything that you're…
Michael Stillman: I guess what I would… what I would say here, what I would ask, Claude or Codex to… to do is to say, really, the point is…
Michael Stillman: that, simple angry, there is a contract, and and it does involve lifetime, so if that is mentioned somewhere else, there should be a pointer to it here. You know, like, there should be an at sign 2, like in the Macaulay 2 language, that will take you from here to that description.
Michael Stillman: Arithmetic is also… that's fine. Arithmetic is being done, consistently over different rings.
Michael Stillman: You know, for many of the operations.
Michael Stillman: The only time that, that allocation is done separately is when you do TO Ring LM and FROM ringLM.
Michael Stillman: And inside of a… inside of a simple A-ring. And those are designed to basically transform the data to garbage-collected memory.
Michael Stillman: Now, there are a slight one exception, which is a little unclear if it's correct or not, is, when you do coefficient ring R as a simple ring, I think it tries… it's a little tricky because it's a… that's already garbage-collected memory, so eventually I would like to remove that and not make it garbage-collected memory, but at the moment.
Michael Stillman: There might be some issue. It seems to work mostly okay.
Michael Stillman: Or all okay, but I don't know exactly why that would be the case.
Michael Stillman: Okay, so, so anyway, that's the simple A-ring stuff, that's good. A-ring glue is… I really dislike the name A-ring glue. I would really, really think that we should change that sooner rather than later to match what it is.
Michael Stillman: And maybe this should be,
Michael Stillman: to the high-level ring interface. Can I see what the actual function… what the actual code in here is, again?
Michael Stillman: Oh, I see, we can't really…
Andrew Tawfeek: I mean, we can keep expanding. I can go to the full…
Michael Stillman: Right, so this is the really… this is really the class concrete ring, as far as I can tell, but let's take a look and see what's after that. And then some definitions for that…
Andrew Tawfeek: Galama Fields.
Michael Stillman: And, yeah, a few other things along these lines.
Michael Stillman: But these are all with ring elements, so this is really concrete ring.
Michael Stillman: Which is actually the thing that takes and… but is it really? Is there other stuff in it after this? That's what I'm worried about.
Andrew Tawfeek: There's.
Michael Stillman: Oh yeah, there's all that… there's all that, translation stuff. This is the stuff that maybe Doug is working on, this lift and promote…
Michael Burr: I haven't worked on the concrete ring stuff yet, but… So
Michael Burr: Parts of this have been adjusted.
Michael Burr: to be tran… to be templated. But that…
Michael Burr: I think we had a discussion last time.
Michael Burr: Because that's a huge switch table, it's not on an enum, so it's basically just integers.
Michael Burr: It's not a… it's not a huge cost in that switch. That table itself might add.
Michael Stillman: No, I know.
Michael Burr: The only… pretty effective.
Michael Stillman: The trouble with it is, is if, each thing has its own, like, local memory that it needs.
Michael Stillman: And then, and then the question is, how does one handle that? So I… it probably handles it well.
Michael Stillman: But, but anyway, that was just one issue.
Andrew Tawfeek: Is templating only just, like, an aesthetic change to the code without changing any functionality?
Michael Stillman: Well, you know, there's… calling it aesthetic is one thing, but it actually generalizes it so it's easier to add other things. So, is it adding new, new stuff at the moment? You know, new functionality to the moment? Probably not, but, but it will enable that.
Michael Stillman: So this… it looks to me like this… this should be called Concrete Ring, or concrete rings, and actually, I don't know which it should be called. Concrete Ring, I guess, right? We're using the type name switch to, wait, what is the dash name called? It's called.
Andrew Tawfeek: Kaboom.
Michael Stillman: What is it?
Michael Stillman: Kebab case, kebab case.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah.
Michael Stillman: So, so it really should probably be that. And if there are other types in there, that's fine, but I think that that seems to be what this is.
Michael Stillman: In some ways, I would like to get rid of that mutable matrices include line also. That's a very unclean thing, but the trouble is, is it's much easier to create an immutable matrix when you've already… when you've already drilled down to whatever class you're dealing with.
Michael Stillman: So, once you know what the template class is. And I wish there was an easier way of doing that.
Michael Stillman: And so then we wouldn't have to include matrix stuff inside of here.
Michael Stillman: But at any rate…
Andrew Tawfeek: I was also gonna mention regarding these headers that if we want them to take a specific shape or format, we could provide kind of, like, a template format, and… or just, like, edit one file ourselves, and then ask it to base everything off that. If we want, like, explicit, like, oh, it should mention, like, the general overarching, like.
Andrew Tawfeek: where does this fit in, the other things that reference it, etc. Like, if we create one template and just feed it to it, it'll just generalize that.
Michael Stillman: I think that's a great idea. I think that's a great idea.
Michael Stillman: Now, the one thing that probably we would like to make sure we do is we have, just like in Macaulay 2 code, having lots of C also, so you can easily click from one to the other. Now, maybe, it will already have some of that stuff in there, I'm not really sure about that.
Michael Stillman: But typically, when Macaulay 2 auto-generates these stuff, it usually puts it in a bad place, because it's not quite where you want it. So…
Michael Burr: So those are, like, the header… that's a discussion on…
Michael Burr: like, the individual files, a short description. There's also a ARings.md that Andrew's been working on.
Andrew Tawfeek: Oh, yes.
Michael Stillman: So yeah, that's probably a good one.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, so…
Michael Burr: We probably won't want to go through the whole thing right now.
Michael Burr: Well, maybe we will, but it's,
Michael Burr: Again, feedback is really important here.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, it's supposed to be for someone wanting to make their own A-ring from scratch.
Michael Stillman: Yeah.
Andrew Tawfeek: Like, the bare minimum.
Andrew Tawfeek: Supposedly. Also generated, but yes.
Michael Burr: Also, wanna just, like…
Andrew Tawfeek: Generated.
Michael Burr: Do you want to look at this now, Mike, or is this something you want to look at offline, or what would be helpful?
Michael Burr: Good use of time.
Michael Stillman: That's a good question, I'm not really sure.
Michael Stillman: Minimal class shape, okay, good, it has all that stuff in it. So, the only issue is… wait a second, I'm missing… we're missing some stuff in here.
Michael Stillman: Can you go back?
Michael Stillman: No, there's the two RingElem from RingEllum. Those are, oh yeah, the const one.
Michael Stillman: I always forget what the… from ring elm const.
Michael Stillman: Is a little bit weird, but…
Michael Stillman: I forget why we needed that. It just… we… we had a rough time with some of the type, munjin.
Michael Burr: And some of this is actually different now,
Michael Burr: This doesn't reflect Doug's changes, this one.
Michael Stillman: Oh, I see, you're right. Now, instead of set from long, set from this, it's just set of element type result come along, right?
Michael Burr: And I think that… The other type of setting?
Michael Burr: is now copy.
Michael Burr: So, like, the from ring out.
Michael Stillman: Oh, yeah, yeah.
Michael Burr: comment right now.
Michael Stillman: Good name, actually. Well, actually, there's copy and… so SAT actually… so what does SAT do? There's init set in the GMP world, right? So you have… init actually sets it up to be a usable object, which is usually the zero object.
Michael Stillman: Init set takes something that has not been initialized and initializes it. Set takes something that has been initialized.
Michael Stillman: And… changes its value.
Michael Burr: Yeah, so that's a… I think that Doug has… I'm… I looked through the code. Doug has been working to at least get all the setters.
Michael Stillman: No, that's great.
Michael Burr: because, like, RR and RRR and RRI, they have their own sets As well, from, like.
Michael Burr: Wheels can set things, and so having Avoiding having multiple
Michael Burr: Copies of that is a good thing.
Michael Stillman: Yep.
Michael Stillman: So each one has their own set of, templates that… that worked, okay.
Michael Burr: or its own set of, I guess, overloaded functions it has, and the template will choose the correct one.
Michael Stillman: Right.
Andrew Tawfeek: Accidentally submitted a review to discard, yes.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay. I am… I'll note down the… Doug changed these, but oh, but this being updated would take just a second, once I… but.
Michael Burr: register.
Andrew Tawfeek: for instance, Codex know that, the function's names have been changed. We can also add comments throughout this minimal class shape, like what you were mentioning.
Michael Stillman: Yeah.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay, so…
Michael Stillman: I mean, like, for instance, at the very top… I mean, probably, like, compute hash value is a different thing than the characteristic and text out. So characteristic and text out should probably be…
Michael Stillman: Probably, you know, compute hash values should not be in with those two functions.
Michael Stillman: I mean, I understand that it probably was when you saw it.
Michael Stillman: But it involves element types, which none of this other stuff, which those things do not. Those are more what's going on at top level. Actually, the size T characteristic is also a little annoying, because what if it's larger than the characteristic?
Michael Stillman: And what if… sorry, what if the characteristic is larger than a size T? Okay, that's a bit annoying.
Andrew Tawfeek: Hmm.
Michael Stillman: Eventually, I'd like to remove all the buffer things and just use C++, Methods for doing…
Michael Stillman: This kind of stuff.
Michael Stillman: But… because there's no point in having another…
Michael Stillman: Thing, but that's a… that's a different, issue for this.
Andrew Tawfeek: Let's see if I go down a bit more…
Michael Stillman: The other thing that's actually worthwhile, maybe, is that if you're actually using these things in code.
Michael Stillman: You might want to be using the… Ring Elem.
Michael Stillman: type, or something like that. Capital ring, capital LM, or I forget what it's called, but where it actually… you give it the ring and an element type, you know, so you can actually… it will have the ring with it, or something like that, so it won't… you won't have to… then you can actually just call functions like operator plus, operator plus equals, you know, stuff like that, on all
Michael Stillman: all these things.
Michael Stillman: That, that class, I believe, exists, but there's… there might be two versions of it. One of them is in the, unit tests stuff that, in fact, when we were dealing in Georgia, I think we… we actually put that in, so…
Michael Stillman: Hmm.
Michael Burr: Thus far, we've been going for… Low-hanging fruit that's,
Michael Stillman: Yep, no, this is… this looks awesome. This looks really good. And having… even having something that you can read through to get yourself grounded like this is just… just totally awesome.
Michael Stillman: Let's see, quick… it's something I probably should sit and just, go through and mark up, or something like that, and then give you comments, because, let's see…
Michael Stillman: Quick checklist. Choose the closest existing A-ring and copy its structure. That's certainly… that's certainly a generally good rule, even though it goes against the whole dry principle, right? But, any case, decide between simple A-ring and custom ring interface wrappers. I'm not sure I understand what that…
Michael Stillman: Means… In what way would… is that mentioned up above? Is that.
Michael Burr: I don't know what it is, either.
Michael Stillman: I think the first thing… so notice how we have these constant, static const ring ID equals, and then we have all this stuff? I think the very first thing you have to do is add a new thing to the ring ID enum type.
Michael Stillman: And I can't remember if it's an enum type now, or if it should be an enum type. I can't remember if I did this before enum classes were around.
Michael Burr: I'm almost certain it's Enum.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, okay, enum class or enum?
Michael Burr: Enum, I think.
Michael Burr: I'll check.
Michael Stillman: We might want to make it enum class eventually, but that we can, do as a,
Michael Stillman: So what's the difference between enum and enum class? Enum class…
Michael Stillman: Enum defines new symbols at top level of wherever you are, whereas enum class is just in the class, so they don't conflict with each other. But you typically have to have, like, A ring type, colon colon, you know.
Michael Stillman: QQ or, you know, whatever it is that we want, rationals or so on. So it's a little more verbose in a certain sense, but it's also just a little safer and a little better, packaged.
Michael Stillman: Define ring ID, element type. So, when you define ring ID, you actually have to change the innum class wherever it is. And again, I'm not 100% sure it's there. So, constructor data and lifetime management.
Michael Stillman: You know what I would almost do for this? This is almost… unless someone really has any… these things don't…
Michael Stillman: it would be good to have an example underneath each one of these things. Like, what does that even mean? You know, and, I think that, when you're first learning this stuff… now, maybe it's already in there, above, and this is just a summary.
Michael Stillman: But, using just names like lifetime management doesn't really tell you what to do.
Michael Burr: I just checked, it's just an enum.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, okay.
Michael Burr: It's in chat, if he wants.
Michael Stillman: How many M's is in your ad comments?
Andrew Tawfeek: How many what?
Michael Stillman: Gems.
Michael Stillman: Oh, it's only 3Ms in a row.
Michael Stillman: forums and eroded me.
Andrew Tawfeek: I wasn't paying attention.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay. Okay.
Michael Stillman: Okay, let's see. Anyway, define those things. Implement ring LM conversion, garbage collection ownership for pointer-backed results.
Michael Stillman: Construction from ZZQQ.
Michael Stillman: Predicates… Comparison time core, printing random elements, and evaluation.
Michael Stillman: Wire the ring into build files and factory code.
Michael Stillman: What do you mean by factory code? That's a… is that C++, meaning of, like, design, you know, patterns factory, or is that factory is in the, package factory?
Michael Stillman: I don't… I think you probably mean the, a factory code
Michael Stillman: It's probably a little too jargony for people that are doing this.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, let's just mentioned in one other spot. What is factory code?
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay, yeah, I don't know…
Michael Stillman: So I think what it means is in… you need to put it in certain places. It might be nice, actually, to say, e.g, you know,
Andrew Tawfeek: ringing.
Michael Stillman: I mean, one of them is in vector arithmetic, so any new A ring type has to be in vector arithmetic.
Michael Stillman: It might not be mentioned here.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay.
Andrew Tawfeek: And promote lift, dispatch unit… someone mentioned units left last time.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, that's actually good. Actually, to tell you the truth, I would put that way up above, but
Michael Stillman: And then you make the unit tests, and then you… then you get them to work. But that's just a,
Michael Stillman: Test-driven thing.
Michael Stillman: Wait, what does the last one say? Run the aiming test and at least the relevant engine Macaulay 2…
Michael Stillman: Smoke tests. So, whenever… I always know that something is AI-written if it uses the word smoke test, because it does it for me all the time, and I… and I understand what it means, generally speaking. So, so… but the question is, do our… do our people know what that means? Do you know what a smoke test is?
Michael Burr: Alright!
Michael Burr: I assume it means where there's smoke, there's fire, so if there's something.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, it's basically… will it work… does it even… if… can you create one of these things, or will it just, you know, crash, or something like that? So, you know, it,
Michael Stillman: But these are actually pretty good, checklists.
Michael Stillman: Okay, add a ring ID and a ring.hp.
Michael Stillman: So… hmm…
Michael Stillman: and add factory support and interface slash avring.cpp. So, we'd have to… I think I would change that to say, what does that mean?
Michael Stillman: Actually, I don't know what it means. I sort of know what it means, but it's kind of a vague term.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, so everywhere that says factory…
Andrew Tawfeek: Which apparently is… In a few places, and even the headers, mention factory code.
Michael Stillman: Right. So, but, I mean, there are some places where… where factory code is basically where you have something that's going to dispatch on all the types, my guess.
Andrew Tawfeek: the.
Michael Stillman: Creates such a… something from…
Michael Stillman: you know, from a… from a general, thing that… so it's essentially dispatching to create. I mean,
Michael Stillman: But I'm being vague, because I don't know which ones these are referring to.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay.
Andrew Tawfeek: And I think that's everything in this PR. It's just this Markdown file, and then headers on the HPP files.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, so, so let's see, so which, where should I actually go grab this file and take a look, or do you want to put something in, Zuloop, about where I should look?
Andrew Tawfeek: But this is…
Michael Stillman: This is in, document A-ring headers.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yes.
Michael Stillman: So it's a draft pull request.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, just so we can keep editing it until, everyone is happy with it.
Michael Stillman: And it's number 61?
Michael Stillman: And that's…
Andrew Tawfeek: Don't…
Michael Stillman: To… onto my.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yes, yes.
Michael Stillman: Wonder.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yes.
Michael Stillman: Hearing branch.
Michael Burr: So I just…
Andrew Tawfeek: decide.
Michael Burr: I just linked the, I linked that… this pull request on, chat.
Michael Stillman: Okay, awesome.
Michael Stillman: On, Zulip, you mean?
Michael Burr: No, no, on Zoom chat.
Michael Stillman: Oh, okay.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, because in both places.
Michael Stillman: Okay, good.
Michael Burr: in digital lip history as well.
Michael Stillman: So, actually, so…
Michael Stillman: these… all these other things, it seems… and all these other A-ring things, I'm… we should take a look and see how the doxygen does, but really, it would be really good if each one immediately referred you to this… the general A-ring stuff, so that you wouldn't… you wouldn't have to keep repeating that.
Michael Stillman: And and it would be a link, so you could easily check it out if you forget or don't.
Michael Burr: It was not in the 1931.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, that's all I have on my end. Yeah, go, sorry, go ahead, Michael.
Michael Burr: I mean, after this discussion, I have an… I have, there's a pull request from Doug that we haven't talked about yet that I can also go over.
Michael Stillman: Okay.
Andrew Tawfeek: Stop sharing.
Michael Stillman: Anyway, that's great. That's, I think that making the A-rings palatable and, and actually, I think having an example in there would be pretty good, you know, for… or at least…
Michael Stillman: You know, of what to do.
Andrew Tawfeek: also speak.
Andrew Tawfeek: Oh, sorry, please go ahead, yeah.
Michael Stillman: No, I'm just trying to think of, I mean, one… we could take a simple one and do it, you know.
Andrew Tawfeek: Hmm, poor.
Michael Stillman: or one that has a little more complication. Like, even the RRI one is probably a good one, because it's a little more complicated. On the other hand.
Michael Stillman: Y-you know…
Michael Stillman: I don't know, I'm not sure. But that one might be a good one to use as an example.
Michael Stillman: Hmm.
Andrew Tawfeek: I also wanted to mention, just since this is an engine meeting, and this would be gone by next week, between this and, like, the next few days, Claude Fable5, they're… the one that the government pulled back on.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Andrew Tawfeek: Anthropica died, and then now it's re-released, again. But it… up until, like, next week, and then it'll become extremely expensive to, like, use it. So, if we wanted to…
Andrew Tawfeek: if there's anywhere in the engine that it feels like worthwhile, having an insanely super smart, powerful AI just go through and do a giant chunk of work, like, between now and next week is the ideal time.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, I mean, once it becomes over $1,000 or $10,000 a month, then we're not… it's not going to be so good, right? So I don't know what price they're going to set it at.
Andrew Tawfeek: I mean, between now and next week, anyone who has a subscription has access to it. It uses up tokens pretty fast, but, like, it's still fine, like, it's still pretty usable. But I think after, like, you know, in, like, 4 days from now, I think, it'll be switched to, like, essentially API calls, where it's gonna be…
Andrew Tawfeek: $10 per 1 million token input, and then $50 per 1 million token output. 1 million tokens is roughly 300…
Andrew Tawfeek: thousand English words, roughly. So, like, it's gonna get, like, very expensive quickly.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, yeah, right.
Michael Stillman: Yeah.
Andrew Tawfeek: But yeah, so if there's anything in Engine that, like, would otherwise require a whole team of eyes to look at,
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah.
Michael Stillman: That's actually an interesting question. So, so what things… so first of all, just having it really try to understand the structure, and maybe even suggest how could we modernize the C++ code, and so on, but maybe that's something that the usual ones can do fairly easily.
Michael Stillman: In fact, I know that on any one of those things, it can do it pretty easily.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah.
Michael Stillman: Having it… if it could give us a reasonable way to,
Michael Stillman: If you could give us a roadmap on how to get rid of the garbage collector.
Andrew Tawfeek: Lower level.
Michael Stillman: So, are you familiar with how… where things are garbage collected now, and…
Andrew Tawfeek: No, I have heard it brought up in almost every meeting, the infamous garbage collector. I don't actually know how it works, or why it's a tutorial.
Michael Stillman: Carbage collector is the Bohm-Demmers, incremental, garbage collector, and, and what… it works, it does not know anything about the data at all.
Michael Stillman: And so, what it does is it looks at things that look like they're pointers.
Michael Stillman: To data it knows about.
Michael Stillman: And then, the data it knows about it can, it can, It can… Oh,
Michael Stillman: you know, it can… it can free and reclaim and stuff like that. So, so if it… but it needs to know how to get all the data that isn't available. So, so…
Michael Stillman: it's a little tricky because it needs to be able to follow pointers and types and things, and if there's an integer in there that looks like a pointer and it follows it, it could get garbage and so on. So, it might accidentally grab more stuff than it could, but overall, it does a pretty good job of doing it. It's pretty slow.
Michael Stillman: I used to think it was about a…
Michael Stillman: I don't know, it was like a 20% hit, I thought, but I would say sometimes it's a multiple times hit.
Michael Stillman: you know, it spends too much time in garbage collection. And, so I… in anything… so, okay, at top level, it's not that big of a deal, but in fact, it's good, because then the user doesn't have to deal with worrying about that kind of stuff.
Michael Stillman: But in the engine, it would be really nice if all A-ring computations, were, were, were not garbage collected, if all matrix… DMAT-type computations were not,
Michael Stillman: It would be nice if mat, matrix, rather, was split into two types, one that is garbage collected and one that is not, and that you have ways of going back and forth.
Michael Stillman: So you can take things that map into a garbage-collected memory or back, and so that if you want to send something to the front end, you can just copy it into garbage-collected memory and ignore it. The other way you could do it is you can have an object that has non-garbage collected memory in it, so that it would leak if you lost that.
Michael Stillman: Okay? And, and didn't do anything with it. But what you can do is you can,
Michael Stillman: Yeah, so what you can do is you can finalize these objects, which means you tell the garbage collector, hey, when this one goes out of scope, I want you to call this other function.
Michael Stillman: Okay? And, and oftentimes, I mean, you're sending it on a per-object basis, but typically it's on a per-class basis, for real, is what's going on. And, so, for instance, a monomial ideal…
Dima Pasechnik: skills.
Michael Stillman: Oops, all of a sudden…
Andrew Tawfeek: Inde amount of… I think…
Michael Stillman: Hey, Dana.
Michael Stillman: So anyway, for monomial ideals and a few other things, they get garb… They get finalized. And
Michael Stillman: And then they get removed when they're, you know, when they're out of scope. So, the question is, if we want to use, Fable, I mean, that would be one thing, would be to… because that's a global piece of information that is hard to get cracked.
Michael Stillman: And I don't.
Andrew Tawfeek: I do.
Michael Stillman: Do that kind of thing or not, but…
Andrew Tawfeek: So, I think maybe with, like, good… so, what I'm thinking is between now and next week, for instance… Here, so I was writing all this, let me make sure it's saved.
Andrew Tawfeek: I can, between this week and next week, kind of work back and forth with Fable and the very small understanding of the engine that I have, and try to put together, like, a proposal, like, largely led by Fable, and guided by the notes he just provided.
Andrew Tawfeek: and see, like, can it propose a plan for how to replace the garbage bucket? So I won't do a pull request of a giant overarching change, but I'll just, like, draft a proposal.
Andrew Tawfeek: that's detailed enough for, like, it has an overview for us to follow, and detailed enough for, like, Opus or one of the lesser agents later to follow, and then we can edit the proposal.
Michael Stillman: So, it's not to get rid of the garbage collector. The garbage collector, but should be… should be set up only for things in the interface directory. All… so, probably the type matrix will be split into two types. One is a garbage collected one, and one's a not. And… but I don't know exactly how to do that, so that would be the thing. One of them is the one that's going to talk to the front end.
Michael Stillman: And one's going to be in the engine only. Engine only, you have to free it yourself. And so whoever… it's got to be managed, kind of like, you would manage it like you would manage Rust objects. So, so it would be that kind of, kind of thing. So.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay.
Michael Stillman: Which means, like, for instance, you use references if you don't have ownership of it, and you don't want ownership. You're just… or, and then you use the object itself, or a pointer to the object.
Michael Stillman: you know, well, you use standard pointer and stuff like that, you know, you… or a unique pointer, rather. And
Michael Stillman: If you own it and things. So, so…
Andrew Tawfeek: Wait, this kid?
Michael Stillman: be nice.
Andrew Tawfeek: This gives me an idea. If we actually… just because a lot of what you're saying feels like it would be very helpful directions for Fable, could… I could also take the snippet of the transcript from this meeting and feed it directly into Fable. Like, essentially your instructions to Fable.
Michael Stillman: What I'm saying is maybe a little too vague, but maybe you could get something useful out of it.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, because I'm worried that, like, my filtering of what you're saying could be, like, misconstrued, and then.
Michael Stillman: You're certainly allowed to do that, as far as I'm concerned, so…
Michael Burr: The meeting is being recorded, so I'll make sure to post the assets sooner rather than later, so that you can
Michael Burr: You can do that.
Andrew Tawfeek: Okay, thank you, yes, yes, and it'll only be.
Michael Stillman: I think it would be pretty good. I mean, I have not tried Fable yet, so is it something I have access to at the moment, if I use.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, no, it literally just opened up Cloud, do slash model, and then one of them should be Fable 5. So there is, of course, the… I mean, there's lots of cool things about it, but there is the dumbing down feature of, if you ask it a question about cybersecurity or biology, it… and it…
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, and most questions about cybersecurity and biology will immediately be dumbed down to Opus, because, they do not, like, worry about cybersecurity attacks, and biological warfare is a legitimate concern. But yeah.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, so I don't think we have to worry about that. So.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah. Well, actually, it does… I have noticed and read that, like, even recently, ironically enough, sometimes some quoting questions get brought down to Opus, which, I mean, for all… it's still fine. Like, I don't…
Michael Stillman: Did you tell when your question has been brought down, or is it…
Andrew Tawfeek: It tells you that, like, your question… so, from what I… I think I read one of the Anthropics articles, and what they have is, like, they have Fable running, and then they have, like, another, like, opus or something running in the background, like, essentially parsing, like, asking, is your quest… is your prompt to the model
Andrew Tawfeek: potentially malicious. Like, potentially. Like, and it's being over-cautious. Like, very, very overcautious. So as a result, like, I remember I was asking it to, like, oh, can you help me, like, work on, like, my resume? I was just, like, trying to, like, change some stuff around, but I had done some work at Georgia Tech that had to do with, like.
Andrew Tawfeek: pathogen classification. He said, we should learn it. And immediately, just, like, the moment it read, it said, like, readResume.pdf, and then your question has been flagged, you've been moved to Opus, because I think it probably read, like, pathogen on my resume.
Michael Stillman: Oh, yeah, yeah.
Andrew Tawfeek: Oh god, oh no. Which is so… It's like… Yeah.
Michael Stillman: It's almost… well, maybe this is… I won't say all this, because it's… this is going to be a posted transcript.
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, no, there's… yeah, we're entering an interesting age. But, but yeah, well, okay, but yeah, long story short, I'll cut out this part from the transcript as well. But yeah, I will take the chunk earlier, and I will, yeah, come… so can you, just for me, mainly, to make sure I'm guiding it correctly.
Andrew Tawfeek: So what is the goal with the garbage collector? You said you wanted to split it for, like, matrices for instance.
Michael Stillman: Okay, so…
Andrew Tawfeek: Yeah, it's.
Michael Stillman: The garbage collector is great for user objects, because then the user doesn't have to worry about whether they exist or not, they just go away when you don't need them anymore, and so on. And it works… that tends to work quite well. But if you're using them in the middle of,
Michael Stillman: actual… computation, it can really slow things down a lot.
Michael Stillman: Now, at first, I didn't worry about it, because I thought it was such a much better memory
Michael Stillman: manager, that it would actually maybe even speed things up, but that was a little naive on my part. Now, on the other hand, I don't know exactly where things stand with all that at the moment.
Michael Stillman: But, but,
Michael Stillman: But I think overall, whenever I can get rid of the… currently, whenever we can get rid of the garbage collector inside of any computation type, then it speeds things way up. And another thing that will… would… that is separate from that is that we have a number of types that are linked lists.
Michael Stillman: like polynomials or linked lists, and that just does not play well with cache. So having a version of it that would, actually, I have versions of these things with Frank Moore, and that we… I would like to make it more central.
Michael Stillman: Where…
Michael Stillman: polynomials are really just a couple arrays, and all the monomials are flattened out somehow, so you don't have to have… so you can imagine doing it a couple ways. One is, you have this whole array of integers, which is all the monomials, and then the other one is where you have an array of objects that are of multiple lengths. And the trouble with that one is.
Michael Stillman: is that you have a two-layer thing, especially if the things are of multiple length, you know, of variable length. And, so…
Michael Stillman: And with polynomials, it's extremely rare that you're going… you're doing random access into the middle of a polynomial. If you're going into that, you're doing the whole thing. So doing it as a single array of,
Michael Stillman: Of, you know, of things that are sort of monomials, but are… where you…
Michael Stillman: You're not sure… you have to read from the front.
Michael Stillman: Now, is that a good idea? I don't know. That might be,
Michael Stillman: I think it might be a good idea. I think it simplifies the code, but on the other hand, it locks you in a little bit, and so is that worth it? I don't know. I'm a little worried about that, because I have certain… I have certain, techniques that I've learned over the years that are… almost all of them are now considered stupid to do. You know, I mean, all the old C things, even the ones that GMP uses.
Michael Stillman: Where you do… the name of… the type is actually an array of length 1, you know, and stuff like that. That's kind of a bit of a hack. You know, and you know, it's useful sometimes, but it's still a bit of a hack.
Michael Stillman: And whenever you're hacking things, it confuses people later on.
Michael Stillman: But, on the other hand, that really gives you cache coherence in, like, just a completely great way, that is not the case in a lot of the types that we're doing.
Michael Stillman: And, yeah, so I can imagine, you know, having a polynomial type that is not linked lists.
Michael Stillman: In fact, I have a couple of them in the system, but not as an A ring type, for instance. Actually, none of the… all the A ring types are currently really basic rings. They're not, like, built-up polynomial rings, except for the coefficient ring R. And that is actually used
Michael Stillman: to create a basic ring of, like, a fraction field, or something like that.
Andrew Tawfeek: Hmm.
Michael Stillman: And… but those are garbage collected, so that whole thing is… all of a sudden, there's one A-ring type that is garbage collected, none of the other ones are. So you have to deal with that issue.
Michael Stillman: So that's kind of annoying.
Dima Pasechnik: So, I understand that, multi… very prenomials in Macaulay 2 are sort of designed to handle Grosvenor bases computations, most of all.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, mostly.
Dima Pasechnik: Because there is nowadays multivariate planeomials from Flint, Which are kind of…
Dima Pasechnik: the opposite, they sort of, they want to do fast arithmetic operations on them, but not necessarily… do…
Dima Pasechnik: specific things, it's kind of…
Michael Stillman: So I think… I actually think that probably the right thing is to have a top-level Macaulay 2 type that uses that, but I haven't played around with it enough to know if it's really… how good it is.
Michael Stillman: And then we can have fast arithmetic and matrices over that.
Michael Stillman: Then if you want to do a Grimner basis, we'll just take that data and translate it. Just flatten it out and use it. And I think that, I didn't do that at first because I didn't want… it seemed like an over… you know, I don't know, it just seemed bad to, you know, to be switching back and forth, representations, but I think in this case…
Michael Stillman: That would probably be good.
Dima Pasechnik: So, I mean…
Michael Stillman: Those kind of things, though, have found to be slow at times, too. So, I mean, they can be heap-based, they can be made heap-based a little easier than flattened polynomials. And so, in that sense, they should be good, but I don't completely buy into the fact that these things are the end-all greatness.
Michael Stillman: And I'm more than happy to be convinced, but I haven't gone through it myself to do that.
Michael Stillman: Hmm.
Dima Pasechnik: Okay, I just wanted to say that people did their benchmarking
Dima Pasechnik: Of those services, compared to… Multivariate polynomials… in singular, which are…
Michael Stillman: They're the same thing as what you use, essentially.
Dima Pasechnik: the M.
Michael Stillman: Maybe a little better than what we use, even.
Dima Pasechnik: Yes, and…
Michael Stillman: As far as speed goes, yeah.
Dima Pasechnik: In that sense, it's kind of, yeah.
Michael Stillman: And it, and it did well?
Dima Pasechnik: Because it was actually mostly built in the same place, so to speak, so they had to… they had a ways to compare and sort of talk to the original.
Dima Pasechnik: designers of pulling off in a hip factory, I understand that's probably the…
Dima Pasechnik: low-level implementation in Singular End, in Macaulay too, right?
Michael Stillman: We use Factory, but we have… we translate our… whenever you want to factor things, you just translate it to their… their data type.
Dima Pasechnik: Oh, okay.
Michael Stillman: The same data type.
Michael Stillman: But how is it? Is it really that much faster? I mean, I've heard that it sometimes is, but I don't really know.
Dima Pasechnik: Well, I mean, we can ask…
Michael Stillman: Yeah, right, we can even try.
Dima Pasechnik: last month.
Michael Stillman: So that might be actually a fun A-ring to try, is using flint. Actually, any one of the flint rings to make an A-ring out of it would be pretty good.
Dima Pasechnik: Okay, so is there none at all at the moment?
Michael Stillman: No, the, some of the… the… some of the ones that are… the ones that are in Flint.
Michael Stillman: And our A-ring types.
Michael Stillman: are… Well, Z mod P.
Michael Stillman: For word length P. Gawa fields, P to the N, for P small or large. No, sorry, for N small or large, P small, small meaning word length, and,
Michael Stillman: Those are two different, representations in Flint.
Michael Stillman: And, and then I have a couple other representations of them also in, in, in Macaulay 2, and… but the ones that are default are the Flint ones.
Michael Stillman: The integers should be default, but they're not.
Michael Stillman: And the… same with the rationals. They should be to the default. And they're both in, they're just not set as the default. And the reason is…
Michael Stillman: Because of translation back and forth. So, because of the garbage collector, it cannot deal with encoded flint integers.
Michael Stillman: encoded flint integer looks like a pointer, the way they encode it. And, and so…
Michael Stillman: or it doesn't look like one. You know, I figure which way it goes. They have… they, they implement things as integers, and then if it's odd, I think then they shift it over, or something like that.
Michael Stillman: And then put a 1 at the end. But that means that it might not even have… it certainly won't look like a pointer, and it won't be the exact pointer value. So the garbage collector really doesn't know how to use that at all. So, so things that go to the front end have to be GMP integers and, and things like that. So that's…
Dima Pasechnik: Some time ago, there was… it was possible to build flint without this kind of hack, so then it can be collected, right?
Dima Pasechnik: I don't know if it's still the case, or…
Michael Stillman: So, so I don't remember them having it where they switched the… so if they made it so that the pointer was the default type.
Michael Stillman: And then you did an operation to get to the integer. They didn't want to do that, because most integers are going to fit, and, you know, eventually. And if it doesn't, then it's going to take longer anyway, so, you know, you might as well put the effort and the time into that. But… and I don't know if there's a way… I remember, talking to, Bill Hart about it, and I don't… he… he, at the time.
Michael Stillman: I didn't have plans for that, but maybe they did, since then, change.
Dima Pasechnik: Well, Bill Hart is long gone from the.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, no, I understand that, I understand. And, so… so my understanding of where they're going and stuff is a little… is out of date. I don't know the current people so well.
Dima Pasechnik: Is it really not possible with, the cabbage collector to, sort of, to teach it to…
Dima Pasechnik: To, to ignore…
Michael Stillman: Well, actually, that's an excellent question. It might be teachable at this point. So here's another pro… okay, so it might be teachable, but… and maybe Claude or something could help us, figure out how to do that. But, you know, the garbage collection code is…
Michael Stillman: Is, like, kind of a little… a little,
Michael Stillman: tricky, you know? It's, like, not completely trivial code. I'm not sure I personally want to go in and muck around with it.
Michael Stillman: The other thing that was a problem with Flint, and I hope they got rid of it, was they had a way of… because of this GC stuff, they had… they could… they could deal with these things, and
Michael Stillman: So the way they dealt with it was they had a whole other array of all the GMP numbers they were using. So… so you would actually keep the… a list of all the ones that were in use.
Michael Stillman: And that was just a hellhole. That was one of the worst bugs. It took me forever to find this bug. But what happened was,
Michael Stillman: and this thing would get modified inside of the finalization routine. So you want to freeze something, it's a GMP integer in there, it sees that it's in that, so it actually calls the finalized routine. Finalize routine has the list of integers, and it wants to get rid of that. But in the meantime, it's actually freeing a bunch of things, which also might also be calling
Michael Stillman: the, finalized routine, which is being called inside of that, which is actually then rewriting the entire… it wasn't done in a, in a way that was meant to be where you could alias this,
Michael Stillman: this list. So, it just didn't work at all. So,
Michael Stillman: That was actually probably the main reason
Michael Stillman: Oh, well, no. Anyway, that was… that was one of the reasons we wanted to switch our… to… I mean, we do copy… copy from going to…
Michael Stillman: run in things.
Dima Pasechnik: Actually, I just looked at what they have in Flint, and they have a… they have a…
Dima Pasechnik: constant called Flint. He uses GC, so somehow this seems.
Michael Stillman: No, no, I know, but that's the one that is bad.
Dima Pasechnik: So this is the one that is bad in the…
Michael Stillman: I think it used to be bad, and, and,
Michael Stillman: And I don't know if they ever believed me at the time. So, maybe they… I was just totally off… off… off the wall, but I'm pretty sure I figured out the bug, and and they…
Michael Stillman: no one else was really using it, so it wasn't actually under any test, you know, it wasn't being tested at all, so… except when we were using it. So I don't know if anyone else is using that.
Michael Stillman: But all that… that's what… what that did was it kept all of these things. The trouble… the other trouble is, is if there is no pointer to it.
Michael Stillman: Okay.
Michael Stillman: then what happens? It gets garbage collected. So the way around that wasn't to switch the integer type so that the pointer was the default version. The idea was you made an array of it, and then you made that one of the GC roots, so it could actually tell if that existed or not.
Michael Stillman: And, and then you got rid of it from that list, But,
Michael Stillman: But it had some, it had various problems. Like, it… the function internally could change that list, and then… but it could also free other things, which would also then change the list, so…
Dima Pasechnik: Do you know how it worked in Flint, in the sense that how can they… enable, GC.
Dima Pasechnik: So they have to make the pointer not look like pointer from…
Michael Stillman: No, no, that's… what I said is that… so, having the pointer not look like a pointer is actually okay.
Michael Stillman: If, the garbage collector can see the pointer somewhere else.
Michael Stillman: So, and so that was why you had an array of all the allocations that you did. And, and then you would try to keep reusing that. So, you know, in lots of applications, there aren't that many integers in use, so that would be not a large thing. I mean, Macaulay, too, that could easily be a hundred million, or hundreds of millions of,
Michael Stillman: Of, like, you know, it's not so… not so good, but, huh.
Michael Stillman: But, you know, it's, but that was… then that sort of worked, except for the… in con… if you didn't use finalization, it worked fine.
Michael Stillman: Okay? Might not have been completely performant, but it… but it worked. But as soon as you, you put finalization into it, it,
Michael Stillman: at least the way the finalization is implemented. And…
Michael Stillman: I mean, sorry, the use of finalization in Flint was implemented. Maybe it's been fixed now. That was a long time ago. I mean, that was easily…
Michael Stillman: 5, 6 years ago, and I haven't gone back to look at it because we switched it around so we don't need to use flint in garbage-collected mode.
Michael Stillman: Except it would be nice, maybe, for what we're talking about here, to be able to do that.
Michael Stillman: It's an interesting question, though.
Michael Stillman: But at any rate, so we do have Z and Q. no other types of… so,
Michael Stillman: for instance, there… other… obviously, like, number fields would be good to put in. Frank and I started doing that, but actually, it was kind of annoying. That was another issue I had with Flint, is that
Michael Stillman: the,
Michael Stillman: it was hard to sometimes get at data, because the calls for all these different rings were not very orthogonal to each other, so… so, some had functions and some didn't. And, so it was actually kind of,
Michael Stillman: a little uneven that way. So, we actually, eventually just… we got busy with other stuff and gave up. But that would be a good app… that would be a good one to try, or… or the multivariate polynomial. I'm doing something like that, that would be great.
Michael Stillman: I would like to get more of the flint rings inside of Macaulay, too. I think it would be really good.
Dima Pasechnik: I'm sure that people who don't…
Dima Pasechnik: Numerical algebraic geometry might be interested in, so, strings which uses… which use their interval arithmetic.
Michael Stillman: In fact, I think we already do that kind of stuff.
Michael Stillman: Is that a flint type that we're… you're referring to? You do it, or…
Dima Pasechnik: Okay, okay, so there is… in Flint, there is a slightly different model of interval arithmetic that is called, ball.
Michael Burr: have ARB.
Dima Pasechnik: arithmetic, yeah?
Michael Burr: ARB is partially in Macaulay 2, it's not exposed at the front end, but it is absolutely in the D language.
Dima Pasechnik: Okay, I mean, ARP is nowadays just a part of Flint, so in that sense, it's not.
Michael Burr: covering.
Dima Pasechnik: So… so the ring sounds…
Michael Stillman: And what is a part of Flint? RR?
Michael Burr: Oh, yeah.
Dima Pasechnik: our P…
Michael Stillman: marble.
Dima Pasechnik: It could be a separate project, but now it's part of Lint.
Michael Burr: we have our asotype at the D level, we haven't fully exposed it at the top level, but it's… it's there.
Michael Stillman: It's in D or in A?
Michael Burr: D.
Michael Burr: It's not a neighboring type.
Michael Stillman: That would be probably pretty easy to, do, right? I mean… or is it worth it, or not worth it?
Michael Stillman: Might not be worth it, I don't know.
Michael Burr: That's the…
Michael Burr: that's the thing to think about, is it worth it? But other than that, it's… it's at least partially there.
Michael Burr: I was hoping, we are running short on time.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, I would like…
Michael Burr: to…
Michael Burr: I was thinking of doing a brief overview of Doug's pull request. I can't answer all the questions on it, but I just wanted to at least show it for a minute.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, that sounds good.
Michael Burr: So…
Michael Burr: This is the most recent one that Doug was working on. You can see it's going for… it's…
Michael Burr: Losing about 200 lines?
Michael Burr: What is happening here is he's using variants, and so…
Michael Burr: First thing is to have these variants.
Michael Burr: And… He's got.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, I understand how to use variants, so that's, that looks good.
Michael Burr: Then, instead of this… Immense switch statement.
Michael Burr: He has this.
Michael Stillman: This is just a visit, right? So you still have to have the functions. So, so where are the functions?
Michael Stillman: Oh, no, he's doing a from ring element, and then a…
Michael Stillman: Oh, this is the Ring Ellen ver- wait, sorry, what is this version doing? Okay.
Michael Burr: I think this is.
Michael Stillman: This is a function taking auto things. What are these things? What's the RF… RPTR?
Michael Burr: our… our PTR?
Michael Stillman: I see it says auto PTR.
Michael Burr: So it's…
Michael Stillman: Oh, I see, no, that's the function call, sorry.
Michael Burr: Like, coming from above…
Michael Stillman: So this is at ring level with ring elements, okay?
Michael Burr: This is in the promote. Yeah, so this is the promote, so you've got a ring, you've got an FR, and you've got a result.
Michael Stillman: Oh, yeah, okay, that makes sense to do this as a variant. Okay, so, so… and then, wait a second, go back up for a second. Oh, absolutely. To all those ones that are… no, just all that list of stuff. No, no, down below. See all these promote… promoter things?
Michael Stillman: Yes. These are, so we have all these functions that will take a ring R and a ring S, and then, and then promote it at the A ring level, right?
Michael Burr: Right.
Michael Stillman: And this is taking… this is the scaffolding to do it for rings. And he wants to do standard variant on those. That sounds… Yes. That sounds actually pretty good to me, although I might like to look at the details of it.
Michael Burr: The only thing that I'd be concerned about is that this is a switch statement on integers, which potentially could be very fast.
Michael Burr: because…
Michael Stillman: Yeah, that's pretty fair.
Michael Burr: because… Because, well, it's an enum, so those are just… Unsigned in, essentially, so…
Michael Stillman: Yep.
Michael Burr: It could be a… there could be tricks that the switch statement is using that we might lose by doing.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, to tell you the truth, that's something that I would like to go over anyway, because we're doing this for the, for Grubner basis stuff. We're using a standard variant inside of some of the computations for doing, coefficient stuff.
Michael Stillman: And it's kind of,
Michael Stillman: I did a… I did a switch… I did a test of doing it via virtual function calls and via standard variant. And actually, the virtual function call might have been just a tad shorter… a tad faster than the standard variant code.
Michael Burr: If I'm reading it right, this gives all sorts of setup, and then it tries to promote, and if it can promote, it does, and if it… if it… if this fails, return false, otherwise…
Michael Burr: It's probably moving… it's probably doing this on the variables itself, so we don't even have to have a…
Michael Burr: We may not have a return, even.
Michael Stillman: Right, now there is a slight issue, that that… this means you have to have all n squared things defined. And…
Michael Stillman: We might have had that before, too, but we might have also been able to just… we had these defaults where you can return false.
Michael Burr: I think there's some defaults that are set, that there's a template, a default template.
Michael Stillman: You know, if you have 10 things, and you're doing 100 different functions, it's not, like, that big a deal.
Michael Stillman: Once it gets to be 50, rings, then maybe it's a little bigger deal. Boom.
Michael Burr: The other thing is, Doug was saying that this…
Michael Burr: made the syntax uniform across all the rings, and forced it to have the correct syntax, so it.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, that's actually, that's actually pretty good. So, can you tell me… so this type name, standard DK, decal type of R1, I forget what DK does, for decal type.
Michael Burr: I have never… I have not used this before, so… and this is Doug's pull request, so I cannot…
Michael Burr: I don't know much about, variants.
Dima Pasechnik: So, is, is, the variant is just kind of… C++, you know, union thing.
Dima Pasechnik: Yeah, that's right. It more than that.
Michael Stillman: So, the variant is… that's all it is, right? It's a, it's a… in most, most languages, like, Pascal used to have, you know, that was the only way you did a union type, was with variants, and you… you had the type at all times.
Michael Stillman: It was only C that decided to go with the union type without telling you which one it was… which one it was. Which,
Michael Stillman: I think, really caused large amounts of,
Michael Stillman: problems. So, but in any case,
Michael Stillman: So the standard variant, that's all it is. But what makes it kind of really work well is this, standard visit function.
Michael Stillman: That allows you to
Michael Stillman: Sort of, like, generalize over which, you know, any one of the variants it is, as long as you have the function calls.
Michael Stillman: There. So, in this, little piece of green code here, there's that, this one is the MyLift, I guess. So, on line 662, that is a… you have a whole bunch of ones, those are all overloaded,
Michael Stillman: functions on different types. I guess they could also be themselves templated, whatever, but in any case, you have… those… all those things make sense.
Michael Stillman: And the standard visit is just essentially dispatching both arguments to be their low-level things.
Michael Stillman: And,
Michael Stillman: So it's,
Michael Stillman: So, in some ways, it's pretty good, but you do have to have the function defined for every single one of the arguments.
Michael Stillman: Bye.
Michael Burr: And again.
Michael Stillman: got that somewhere. So, and… Defined us in this…
Michael Burr: Defined is in the sense of there is a default template somewhere.
Michael Stillman: Yeah, so you have to be a little careful, so when you're using…
Michael Stillman: templates, and you're using standard… Variance, and you're using template classes.
Michael Stillman: they, they don't always play well together, and, so you, you, you aren't allowed to do certain things. Now, in fact, to… but that said, if… so if I did this as a, a, as a,
Michael Stillman: as a virtual function call to all these different possible things, I can do that. And, and then it works out pretty good.
Michael Stillman: But actually, the standard visit version, the standard variant version, allows you to…
Michael Stillman: to get more oomph from templates. Do you want that oomph?
Michael Stillman: Probably not, because it just makes it more complicated, but it does work. And actually, Frank and I were using that in some of the Grimner code somewhere.
Michael Burr: That's what my husband… I don't…
Michael Stillman: So this is actually looking pretty good. I have to, I'll go over it with him and go over each line, because I would like to make sure that this is.
Michael Burr: Pretty hot.
Michael Stillman: But it looks very good, I have to say, I'm…
Michael Burr: It looks a lot better than an awful switch statement if it works.
Michael Stillman: So, you know, it looks better, oh, okay, Andrew, see you. Actually, I'm gonna have to go soon, too. Yeah, I know.
Andrew Tawfeek: Spring.
Michael Stillman: the.
Michael Burr: enter.
Michael Stillman: And but… but on the other hand.
Michael Stillman: there's code that is simple code like that, that is easy to understand, even if it's longer code. But maybe it's not easier to understand. So I actually like this… this version looks to me pretty straightforward.
Michael Stillman: I don't know why the decay is necessary there.
Michael Stillman: And I'm actually suspicious that it's not, because that's the kind of thing that Claude likes to put in, you know, extra stuff like that. But maybe it's doing it for good reasons. Do you know what I mean? Maybe it's doing it because,
Michael Stillman: Because I'm just too naive in my C++ use.
Dima Pasechnik: So what is this decay? I've never seen it, actually.
Michael Stillman: So DK is, like, if you take a type.
Michael Stillman: I don't know if it… it might have to do with whether there are references on it, or const on it, and stuff like that, and… and then it… it either strips them off, or… But I think that DK is doing something slightly different than that, but I forget.
Michael Burr: Well, I just wanted to just…
Michael Burr: Make sure to show this, because this is something that would be a big change.
Michael Burr: But it's definitely…
Michael Stillman: Oh yeah, no, no.
Michael Burr: worth considering.
Michael Stillman: Anything to make this code, better would be great. Actually, to put it on the transcript, also, reorganizing the linear algebra code,
Michael Stillman: it would be very nice. Even when we did it, which was about 15 years ago, it was… it seemed like it was… I wasn't even 100% happy with it at the time, but I didn't know any better way of doing it. So, so it would be nice to maybe get,
Michael Stillman: Claude, Fable involved in trying to find a better way of doing that, organization.
Michael Burr: Also, when… when you… when… on a week that you can make it, and we have a good number of people, it'd be good if you gave a… a tour, so that we knew what…
Michael Stillman: Yeah.
Michael Burr: It's there.
Michael Stillman: As far as that goes, by the way, next week is… I won't be able to do it. I'll be traveling, in fact, going to Salzburg.
Michael Stillman: And then…
Michael Burr: It's funny.
Michael Stillman: The next week after that, I actually will be around, I think.
Michael Stillman: 1 o'clock…
Michael Burr: Tough for me.
Michael Stillman: Eastern Time in the U.S. that week. Soon after that, I'll be, going to,
Michael Stillman: to this ICMS, meeting, but, but before that,
Michael Stillman: Yeah, I'll have just gotten back from Vienna, so,
Michael Stillman: But… but I'll be around, so that'll be good.
Michael Burr: Next week will also be tough for me. I'll make sure to put something in Zulip, whether I can make it or not.
Michael Burr: Yeah.
Michael Stillman: Okay, so should I plan on 2 weeks after that? Can you make it that time, or not?
Michael Burr: Well, we'll put in Zulupp and be talking over there. I'll be managing stuff.
Michael Stillman: That sounds good.
Dima Pasechnik: In two weeks, I'm traveling, but next week is okay, and the week after, and then after the…
Dima Pasechnik: in… in 3 weeks should also be okay, I'll have more time.
Michael Stillman: Okay, cool.
Dima Pasechnik: It is so just…
Michael Stillman: Yeah, actually, after that, I might actually be okay on Friday as well after that, but I'm not sure yet. So, depends when I'm driving.
Michael Stillman: Oh, actually, there is a slight… No, I think that that's…
Michael Stillman: Yeah, actually, I'm pretty sure that…
Michael Stillman: Actually, I'm not sure… 100% sure, but we'll talk about it on Zillip. I think I can do it, I'm not sure.
Michael Burr: I'm gonna turn off the recording now.
Michael Stillman: Okay.